[Music]
hello this is Jim at the house at Pooh
Corner again and there's the camera so I
will look at that camera and we have had
a number of very important guests over
the last few months from geoengineering
to all kinds of imperialistic Imperial
adventures and today your guest is John
Corey aku who is one of my heroes
most of my heroes actually kind of fall
into the whistleblower category from
Daniel Ellsberg whom I interviewed ages
ago and Sibel Edmonds whom I've
interviewed a few times on the radio and
here we are with another very important
whistleblower so important that Obama
threw him in jail and we're going to
talk a little bit about what he did
having to do with the Bush
administration's torture program and
he'll update us on certain status that
where he is and maybe talk a little bit
about mr. Binney and mr. Shipp Kevin
chip and Bill Binney and all right so
let's John tell us a little bit about
yourself and what happened and we'll go
from there
well my name is John Kuryakin I'm a
15-year CIA veteran I was in the CIA
from 1990 through 2014 and resigned in
2014 actually was effective 2015 and
then in 2000 on you know what let me fix
that that's not right 1990 to 2005 9:15
and in 2007 I blew the whistle on the
CIA's torture program I had kept it
inside for four years just waiting for
somebody to come forward and to say
something nobody said anything and fine
I decided that that it had to be out
there and and so I said something in a
nationally televised interview on ABC
News to make a long story short I paid
for it with my freedom I was I was
arrested by the FBI charged with five
felonies including three counts of
espionage coming out of that interview I
hadn't committed espionage and those
charges were dropped but but I ended up
going to prison for 23 months all worth
it in the end
the price was high certainly but it was
all worth it because I thought that this
was this was a war crime a crime against
humanity it was a violation of US law
was a violation of international law
certainly the United Nations Convention
Against Torture and I thought that our
government shouldn't be in the business
of doing it so I got out of prison in
February of 2015 and I've been talking
about it and writing about it ever since
all right now a couple of questions one
is what kind of support or communication
of any kind have you had with your peers
with your former peers and I'm also
interested in the kind of communication
you've had with bill Binney and with
Kevin ship and that's already two
questions and my third one is the Bush
administration handled it one way and
the Obama administration really went
whole hog that's a very important
component of this whole story well to
answer your first question first my
support inside the CIA especially at the
working level has been absolutely
fantastic
70 of my former CIA colleagues signed a
letter to President Obama asking him to
pardon me all 70 signed a second letter
this one to president Trump asking him
to pardon me
so my support inside the agency has been
fantastic this was this
torture program was was a blaspheming
against what we were supposed to stand
for you know when I put my right hand up
in the air and I swore to uphold the
Constitution against all enemies foreign
and domestic I meant it and sometimes
the enemy is ourselves and so I'm glad
to say that I wasn't the only one who
recognized that one of the weird things
about entering the the world of
whistleblowers is that we have something
of a club where we've all become friends
you know Dan Ellsberg is the is the
granddaddy of all modern national
security whistleblowers he's an icon to
all of us and then there's bill Binney
and Kirk Wiebe and Ed Loomis and and Tom
Drake and Jesslyn ray back and so many
others it's known even we've all become
friends we stay in close touch those of
us who are here in the DC area get
together frequently socially and really
you need that support network because
when you blow the whistle on something
relative to the national security
there's nothing in the world that makes
you feel more alone and more isolated
and more endangered than that without
that support you couldn't get through it
you literally couldn't get through it
yeah I'm surprised frankly that more
people charged with these national
security crimes don't commit suicide
than than the handful that we've already
seen um Kevin ship is another one Kevin
it's funny Kevin believed that he was
alone Kevin ship blew the whistle on CIA
malfeasance and they went after his
family for it and finally I reached out
to him after reading his story in The
Washington Post and I said listen buddy
you're not alone you've got some some
friends here you probably have never
even met but you shouldn't be going
through this alone and so we've we've
pulled him into it as well we even have
an organization called VIPs veteran
intelligence professionals for sanity Oh
we right yeah yeah we were policy
recommendations for the president
they're usually ignored but at least we
get ourselves on paper yeah I know
quite well yes Raymond got the support
for people yeah remind me your third
question oh the third question had to do
with the ramping up of prosecutions
against whistleblowers under Obama yes
when when I went on ABC News in 2007 and
blew the whistle I said three things I
said that the CIA was torturing its
prisoners I said that torture was
official US government policy not the
result of a rogue as President Bush had
intimated and I said that the policy had
been personally approved by the
president the FBI began investigating me
the very next day and they investigated
me for a full year from December of 2007
until December of 2008 they determined
in 2008 that I had not committed a crime
and they closed the case not only did
they closed the case they sent my
attorneys what's called a declination
letter saying that they were declining
to prosecute me three weeks later Barack
Obama's inaugurated as president and
styles himself the most transparent
president history he secretly ordered
that the case against me be reopened I
had no idea I was under investigation
again mm-hmm
it was investigated for three more years
and then finally arrested in January of
2012 and charged with those five
felonies and you don't forget that that
espionage is one of the gravest crimes
with which an American can be charged
and if sometimes carries with it the
death penalty so this was a serious
policy decision that the Obama people
made beyond that this isn't just because
they didn't like John Kiriakou beyond
that Obama prosecuted eight national
security whistleblowers in the entire
previous history of the United States
only three whistleblowers were
prosecuted
the espionage act so Obama was almost
three times the number of all previous
presidents combined really Barack Obama
was the enemy of transparency he was the
enemy of whistleblowing really in my
view the enemy of human rights yeah well
then my the question that I have been
wondering about for years and I'll let
you have it is who was ordering Barack
Obama to do this because it just my
brain tells me that Obama couldn't have
cared less but that somehow he was being
pressured to do this and when I follow
when I follow that logic and I have
often in the past as a journalist it
turns out to be someone connect someone
like Jamie Dimon someone connected with
the central banks someone connected with
something to gain and we found that
because of visage we discovered that but
go ahead why could tell you with 100%
certainty it was John Brennan John
Brennan on national security called all
the shots and I'll tell you why it's
actually it's actually an important
lesson I think for future presidents and
that is that the CIA loves inexperienced
presidents they they love them because
when a president is elected and he has
little or no foreign policy or or
national security policy experience that
gives the CIA an opportunity to to
recruit that president and what I mean
by that is if you've just been elected
president you don't know anything about
national security or intelligence today
after the election when you're you're on
your first day as president-elect you're
entitled to a CIA briefing a president's
Daily Brief
briefing that's PDB that's at levels
multiple levels above top secret well as
soon as the CIA gets in front of you and
they say mr. president-elect
we want to tell you about all the cool
things we're doing and they show you
your first blue border report or black
border
or multiple levels over top-secret human
intelligence penetrations of foreign
intelligence services access agents next
to world leaders you know that stuff's
fascinating and it's fun and it's cool
it's exciting and they're able to suck
that president right in and make him one
of the boys Barack Obama head he was a
senator for what four years he wasn't
even one full term as a senator and he
was only on the Senate Foreign Relations
Committee for two years and even then
had no access to classified information
and then on sudden he's the most
important man in the world
so it's it's heady stuff and present
president-elect really loved it
on top of that he had an alpha dog in
the form of John Brennan whispering in
his ear all day long and John Brennan
certainly had his own agenda besides
that I want to make a third point in the
book doubled down by Mark Halperin and
John Holliman it was about the 2012
presidential election Obama is set for
an interview and in that interview he
said two things that I think we're
really telling first he said very
matter-of-factly I never said I was a
liberal and that was true he actually
never did say he was a liberal we said
he was a liberal but he wasn't and then
talking about the drone program he said
kind of wistfully I never had any idea
that I would be so good at killing
people well it's because he never said
he was opposed to the drone program no
he never said he was opposed to long
distance you know cruise missile
launches we we sort of placed that on
him because that's what we wanted to
believe hmm that's the anti Hillary that
we wanted to be elected president and
their Nobel Prize nothing progressive
about him at all on foreign policy
military policy and intelligence mm-hmm
well then two questions come to mind
is that he was clearly Wall Street's
pick and he was practically appointed to
his Senate position it was a coronation
he slid in yeah he was coronated into
the Senate then Citibank
appointed his entire staff essentially
the upper levels of staff and when I
looked at who they were yeah and Jamie
Dimon at all were the ones who did that
picking and I remember I wrote an
article and I said this is not small
it's beautiful you know we're going for
centralization here with all the big
players who have been central central
players right from the beginning and so
I told that to people on my radio
program that you know if you're voting
for Obama I want you to know this and
this was when he was running for
president and anyway in Vermont he was a
shoo-in because you know people don't
care how many Palestinians you kill as
long as you get your anyway so what is
your opinion as to the relationship
between this is a tricky question
between Brennan and wall street meaning
Goldman Sachs at all and and then I'll
throw in another villain which is Muller
Robert smaller and I've done two I've
done to expose about robert muller over
the years going back to 1984 and he is
one piece of work he is my opinion the
number one fixer for the deep state so
go ahead and see what you can do with
those questions yeah I will see John
Brennan John Brennan intellectually was
in over his head John Brennan rose far
beyond what his intellect should have
allowed and it was because he became a
close friend and protege
of George ten most retired directors of
Central Intelligence or directors of the
CIA they became known later on end up on
Wall Street in some capacity
George has become the principal in a
vulture fund in New York City that has
made him rich beyond his wildest dreams
ah Steve kappes who was the number two
at the CIA is doing the same thing right
now for a vulture fund based here in
Washington DC so this is a normal thing
where they go to Wall Street and they
make tens of millions of dollars and
they live happily ever after
John's not done that my own opinion is
that John's not smart enough to do it
so what job has ended up doing is he is
teaching a class at Fordham which is his
alma mater and he's a talking head on
MSNBC and he's on the board of a couple
of smallish defense contractors he's
actually having to work for a living
he's not making anywhere near the money
that his predecessors have made so he
really doesn't have those deep Wall
Street ties not because he doesn't want
them but because he's just not smart
enough to do it Robert Muller I have a
personal beef with Robert Muller
I would think so other was the CIA
director when I was arrested not only
was he the CIA director
you mean FBI director sorry I'm sorry
the FBI director but not only was he
that but he created the John Kiriakou
task force inside the FBI he appointed
12 FBI agents who tapped my phones
intercepted my emails had groups of two
agents in cars following me to work to
church to the grocery store out with my
family
24/7 coverage trying to catch me
committing a crime
I wasn't committing any crimes that went
on for three years they did that in
addition it was John Brennan who when
Obama became president sent a memo to
Eric Holder at the Justice Department
saying charge him with espionage and
then Eric
came back and said my people don't think
he committed espionage
meaning the Muller John Kuryakin task
force and then Brendan responded charged
him anyway and make him defend himself
and then on January the 12th 2012 a
fellow by the name of Peter struck
mm-hmm but he saw me behind my back and
took me to a holding cell underneath the
federal courthouse in Alexandria
Virginia so these same people who are
going after Donald Trump at all are the
ones who after me it is deep state and
you don't have to call it a deep state
you can call it whatever you want
you can call it the state you can call
it the federal bureaucracy whatever it
is the deep state actually exists and
these are the guys who run it okay then
that leads me into the next question
which is well I'll preface it by saying
that I realized as Trump went through
the candidacy and the RNC was trying to
cut him off at the knees and of course
the the Democrats just laughed him off
didn't get it and well I won't go into
it but all the way through until today
as we speak there are elements of what I
will call the deep state I mean they're
right out in the open now so it's just I
feel silly saying the deep sate because
you've got Muller and Brennan and then
the entire the entire DNC you've got you
know Pelosi the whole gang and the New
York Times and the rest of the
mainstream media who seemed to be able
and the CIA who seemed to be able to
have a way of turning Trump from
somebody who was out of the loop who was
trying to demilitarize and and pull our
troops back turn him into some kind of a
madman what is your take on what if
anything happened to Trump and how are
they getting him
to do this I think I know the answer but
I really want to hear from you I think
he was more or less forced into it
because there were so many Republicans
important Republicans who joined that
so-called nevertrump movement mm-hmm so
when Trump finally became president I
mean look at this way Hillary Clinton
had a hundred and seventy five people on
her Middle East transition team right
Donald Trump had 25 people on his entire
transition team and it's because Donald
Trump never thought he was going to be
elected president so he wasn't prepared
for it that coupled with the fact that
there are all these nevertrump erse men
he just simply didn't have enough people
to fill senior level positions at the
State Department the Defense Department
at the White House and so little by
little he had to start bringing these
never Trump errs into the administration
or the never Trump errs by and large
were neo cons who made their bones in
the Bush administration and so little by
little and it was really incremental
they came to the White House they became
assistant secretaries of state assistant
secretaries of defense the next thing
you know they're running foreign policy
not Trump not the White House and not
the people he brought with him from the
campaign and that's how they did it yeah
another thing too you know I've I've
spent most of my adult life dealing with
with senior intelligence officials
senior diplomats generals at the
Pentagon and they can all be very
convincing you know when when you're
getting a briefing on let's say the
situation in Afghanistan or the
situation in Syria the situation in
Libya they can make it sound like we're
winning it we're on the cusp of
finishing this thing off and if you pull
out now it's gonna be a disaster we're
gonna lose our international prestige
people are gonna die so give us six more
months give us 12 more months and then
six four months later they repeat the
same thing and they do every year
year after year after year and the next
thing you know you're bogged down in
some kind of foreign entanglements yeah
and the Democrats are right but right
with that opinion and this the braided
egg one so even worse there's no there's
no real difference between the Democrats
and the Republicans on these foreign
policy issues there there's some minor
tweaks around the edges but they're both
neo cons and neoliberals they all
believe in exactly the same thing and
that is that we really do need to have a
military presence in a hundred and ten
countries around the world we need to
have military bases in 86 countries
around the world we need to have the
newest nuclear weapons and the biggest
ships and the best airplanes and and the
biggest bombs they all believe this
stuff that's 700 countries they're 144
countries in the world and we have 110
we have oh I don't know why I thought it
was 700 I've I had that number stuck in
my head alright well that's a relief
[Laughter]
so okay and getting back to people like
Jamie Dimon and the central banks who
owned Obama what it struck me that they
were panicking as they began to realize
you can see the expressions on the on
the Talking Heads faces they they were
struck dumb and and that kind of
paralyzed mode because they were talking
gibberish as as Trump's numbers went up
so here we have a guy entering the
presidency who was out of the loop and I
think you've explained how they put him
in the loop and how he would be behaving
gradually and I was so disappointed in
him when he appointed some of the people
he appointed it was god-awful and then
he goes back to Reagan he drags up the
bottom of
barrel that an embarrassment to the US I
mean who's who's been more embarrassing
to the US than Bolton except maybe
Abrams was gonna say Elliott Abrams is
at least as offensive and horrible a
human being as John Bolton is yeah I
remember yes Mira legitimate war
criminals legitimate war criminals on
their hands yeah so what why did Trump
do that well like I say there was just
nobody to take these jobs at one point
almost a year into the administration
there were 13 vacant assistant
secretaries of state positions so you
can't have a foreign policy if you have
no Assistant Secretary of State to run
that foreign policy the only thing that
he could do was to start drawing from
either previous administrations more
conservative think tanks and those were
the neocons they're the ones that have
all the money and staff the think tanks
in Washington he really had no choice
yeah well our friend Ray McGovern I
think was one of the ones railing
against this and there were a lot of
good people like Paul Craig Roberts who
were saying what are you doing you know
you have a chance mr. president of at
least appointing decent human beings to
these positions and you're going to the
bottom of the barrel to pull up war
criminals to be in these positions and I
said that Trump can't be that ignorant
but maybe maybe it's a combination of
his ignorance and and his maybe he's
evil like they are I don't know what do
you think about that I think that's a
possibility you know if every mccabe is
to be believed and this passage in his
book he recounts a a meeting at the
White House where they're talking about
foreign policy and then Trump says what
about Venezuela that's the country we
should be a war with no another week and
they have all that oil yeah I know that
quote yeah if that's if that's how you
determine your foreign policy then you
need help from somewhere
unfortunately you looked at the wrong
place for that help
yeah oh we only have a minute 30 seconds
left so ladies and gentlemen I'm sorry I
haven't said his name 100 times John
Kiriakou a whistleblower who brought out
the bush torture program and has been in
the thick of what's happening today ever
since and as I said one of my heroes
along with bill Binney and we will do
another interview with John Kiriakou
when he is free very busy and hopefully
you and I will be fortunate enough to
continue this I think we've hit an awful
lot of key points that of course the
mainstream media and and the alternative
media doesn't even know enough to hit if
they were allowed to do it so closing
words well my pleasure you know I think
we ought to be talking about these
issues because they're important and
nobody else is talking about them so
thanks for having me I look forward to
seeing you again soon okay well thanks
again oh sorry we lost sound okay well
ladies and gentlemen we will be back
with more from John Kiriakou and maybe
even some more whistleblowers as as time
goes by so thanks a lot for listening to
the house at Pooh Corner with Jim Hoge
[Music]
you